<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Performance | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/categories/performance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-06T01:03:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The User Experience]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/05/03/the-user-experience/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T15:26:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/05/03/the-user-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>&ldquo;User experience&rdquo; encompasses all aspects of the end-user&rsquo;s interaction<br/>with the company, its services, and its products.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>JAKOB NIELSEN and DON NORMAN</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/ux-badge.png" width="200"></p>

<p>Over the last couple of the months the company where I am currently employed has
sponsored company wide UX training through the Nielsen Norman Group(NN/g). I also
passed the examinations and I am now UX
Certified(<a href="http://www.nngroup.com/ux-certification#track.">UXC#1007600</a>)</p>

<p>NN/g is at the fore front of evidence based User Experience research. As a software
developer, I found it very sobering that what I and my other fellow coworkers
were building may not be all that comprehensible to the end user of the systems we
engineered. However, this problem was not unique to us. In fact companies such
as Pizza Hut, Amazon, Chipotle and others struggle with it all the time.</p>

<p>Anytime a user experiences frustration or confusion using or ordering a product,
you run a high probability of never seeing them again. We don&rsquo;t set out to build
products that are difficult to use. We want our customers to experience success
and return to us with future business again and again.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the individuals building a product are too close to and too familiar
with the product to realize the difficulties apparent in its use. A creator will
place controls in a certain order and position. Since he has spent so much time
crafting and wiring those controls; what they do will be second nature to him. He
could very well know what each does with no need of labels or cues. However,
another may find these controls counter intuitive and confusing. The order of things
makes no sense and they do not do what he expects.</p>

<p>Another issue is creator pride which blinds us to the faults present. There are
times when we might create something like a piece of art, a dish to eat or another
creation. As the creator we might be blind to poor composition of the art work or the
lack of flavor in a meal which is so apparent to another.</p>

<p>For this reason its important to validate what we build. We must seek out the
brutally honest opinion of the end consumer, of the end user. Does he enjoy using
the product? Does he find it confusing? The way these sort of tests
are conducted so as to obtain statistically valid and actionable results without
influencing the subject is at the core of NN/g training.</p>

<p>Lets view a couple of videos.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nBUWxROnqwA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>The Ring was a Kickstarter funded project with great promises to control all sorts
of other electronic devices through various hand gestures. The reviewer really digs
into them hard for what he perceived as an incredibly poor user experience. He
found the product difficult to use, failing incredibly in delivering its promise.</p>

<p>Takuro Yoshida, the Ring creator, responded to the harsh reviews of his
<a href="https://www.techinasia.com/ring-kickstarter-wearable-ceo-responds-to-criticism/">product</a>.
From the interview, it does appear that there is a user experience disconnect at the
very least with a portion of Ring users. If you read the interview you&rsquo;ll notice this
statement by the interviewer.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Yoshida passed me his ring and I was able to learn six gestures in a matter of minutes. Without his instruction, I probably wouldn’t have realized that I was flicking my wrist too much (you should only move your finger) or moving too much after completing a gesture (you have to hold still for a moment for the gesture to register).</p></blockquote></p>

<p>This seems to indicate that indeed the product is just not that intuitive to
some people. I hope the company manages to address these issues whether actual
or just perceived. I can see how the idea of controlling your electronics
through hand gestures can be very appealing.</p>

<p>Well, I hope you&rsquo;ve enjoyed this. Till next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Problem Solving for Everyday Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/26/problem-solving-for-everyday-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-26T13:31:47-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/26/problem-solving-for-everyday-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/confusion_scrabble.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>I was going to name this article, &ldquo;Algebra for everyday problem solving,&rdquo; but
I was concerned many people would assume this had to do with figuring out the
speed of a train having left the station two hours ago. Well, that&rsquo;s not what this
all about. Instead it&rsquo;s much more interesting.</p>

<p>Lets look at some basic algebra and then I&rsquo;ll elaborate.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">10 + x = 12

therefore

10 + 2 = 12
</code></pre>

<p>If we look at the problem on line 1 above, we see that at first we don&rsquo;t know what &lsquo;x&rsquo; is.
What we do know is that 10 plus that value will yield us 12. So it&rsquo;s very easy to then determine
that &lsquo;x&rsquo; is in fact equal to &lsquo;2&rsquo;. So what just happened here?</p>

<p>What happened is that we had an unknown (x), two knowns (10 and 12) and an
established relationship between them and from that we were able to determine the unknown.</p>

<h2>The Confusion</h2>

<p>A confusion is often made of several unknown factors. The more unknowns the more
confusing the situation can be. Likewise, the more knowns there are the less confusion
there is. This then can aid us in gaining a foothold into the resolution problems.</p>

<p>One must operate from those elements which have the highest degree of certainty and
truth. From that solid foundation we attempt to solve one of the unkowns, then another and
another until all elements are solved.</p>

<p>For example, the police find a dead body? Who is it? How did he die? When? Was it murder?
Who killed him? There are many unknowns. They run his fingerprints and find out who he is.
They take the body to the coroner and get the time of death and probable cause of death.
Now they know it was Joe Burns, he died 48 hours ago and he was struck with a bat
which caused the death. They now have some nice solid knowns to operate from from.</p>

<p>Since they know he died 48 hours ago, they canvas the area looking for witnesses present
around that time. They can also use the time of death to eliminate suspects by
verifying alibis. They can look for a particular murder weapon.
With his ID, they can find his friends and family and ascertain possible
suspects.</p>

<p>Thus the police can begin to solve this mystery from building more and more knowns from
a declining number unknowns.</p>

<h2>Look Out for&hellip;</h2>

<p>One tries to operate from highest known one can achieve. This does not mean the
&lsquo;known&rsquo; is necessarily correct; it&rsquo;s just the most correct datum we have
available. For example in our crime drama, it&rsquo;s possible the
body may have been affected by some process which caused an incorrect conclusion as to
the time of death. Thus shifting the time line of events.</p>

<p>Occam&rsquo;s razor is very often misstated as the simplest answer is usually the correct
one. This is quite an incorrect statement. Actually, the principle states that the answer
with the least number of assumptions is the correct one. Complexity is not the issue,
assumptions are the problem.</p>

<p>So, beware of operating off of assumptions and here-say. The best thing is as direct an observation
as one can obtain. In solving issues at work, solutions have often been delayed by just taking
a coworkers word for it. This is not to say people are not truthful it&rsquo;s just that
we often have issues recalling things accurately or we might miscommunicate what we have
observed.</p>

<p>Play a game of telephone sometime with a group of friends and you&rsquo;ll be amazed how easily
facts are distorted within a few retellings.</p>

<p>Well, I hope this has been of value.</p>

<p>Take Care.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Easy vs Simple]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/19/easy-vs-simple/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-19T16:47:24-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/19/easy-vs-simple</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/easy_street.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>The meaning of words naturally evolve over time. As a consequence certain words
will unfortunately lose their distinctive meaning and become an undistinguished
synonym for another word. This is what I believe has happened with the words
&lsquo;easy&rsquo; and &lsquo;simple&rsquo; which are now used quite interchangeablely. The original
meaning of these words can help us illustrate a very important idea.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start by looking at their definitions.</p>

<h2>Definitions</h2>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>easy - requiring little effort; presenting few difficulties; not difficult.</p></p><p><p>simple - easily done, used, or understood.</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Macmillian Dictionary for Students</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>As you can see these words are very close in meaning today. Let&rsquo;s take a look
at what they used to mean.</p>

<h2>Origins</h2>

<p>&lsquo;Easy&rsquo; originally came from the Latin word ADJACERE which means to lie near. This
makes sense as those things which lie near physically or mentally are easy to
reach.</p>

<p>&lsquo;Simple&rsquo; comes for the Latin word SIMPLEX which means single fold. In other words
something is simple when it consists of very few parts. Thus when something
has little in the way of parts it then is not a difficult thing to grasp.</p>

<h2>Observations</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to point out the origin of &lsquo;easy&rsquo; implies a certain subjectivity. As
things which are easy for me (near my mind) ,due to my experience, may not
be easy for someone else. In contrast &lsquo;simple&rsquo; is more objective. The more parts
and more intertwined and dependent those parts are of a thing, the less simple
that thing is.</p>

<p>For example Spanish is a simple language, Grammatically, it has fewer
irregularities than other romance languages. This would be an objective
statement.</p>

<p>However Spanish is easy for me since it&rsquo;s my first language and
difficult for my wife since she does not speak it. Thus we see easy
take on a more subjective role.</p>

<h2>Okay, so what?</h2>

<p>We are obsessed with the easy at the cost of complexity.The benefits or
detriments can be argued but it is none the less there. It is easy (close, near)
to go to the market and purchase a carton of orange juice but have you ever
wondered how complex (many parts) it was to produce that carton and it&rsquo;s contents?</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s far easier to use power windows but the mechanism has many parts and with
many parts comes the probability that something will go wrong sooner than a simpler
mechanism,  requiring service. It can be easy to ship a package but not so simple to find
one lost in the labyrinth it traveled.</p>

<p>Cheating, stealing and lying are all easy. We gain what we desire immediately.
The consequence is complexity. Keeping track of the lies told, avoiding discovery,
and having people distrust and hate us does not a simple life make.</p>

<p>This trade off between easy and simple is especially of concern to those who
build things such as engineers. Some select at tool or technique because
of it&rsquo;s ease of use yet it may actually lead to a complex structure which is
difficult to maintain and service.</p>

<p>Keep this in mind when doing something because it&rsquo;s easy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build Measure Learn]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/12/build-measure-learn/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-12T14:34:48-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/12/build-measure-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/build-measure-learn.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>Some months ago I came across a list of top books recommended by
successful entrepreneurs. Towards the top of this list was the
book &lsquo;The Lean Startup&rsquo;. I highly recommend this book to anyone
looking to start their own business or anyone involved in management.</p>

<p>One of the major concepts in the lean startup method is what&rsquo;s referred to
as the Build-Measure-Learn feedback loop. The basic idea is a cycle of
of building a product, measuring success then learning from this measurement
and other actions so as to build a better product and finally start
the cycle again. It is a way managing uncertainty and risk.</p>

<p>Realize that it&rsquo;s the speed at which this cycle occurs that most likely
determines success. A startup or new venture has a limited amount of time
and/or funds in order to become a viable concern. Once these resources are
consumed and no other options are present; the startup is done. This is why
speed is of essence.</p>

<p>While the cycle seems straight forward, each of these points on the cycle
has it&rsquo;s challenges.</p>

<h2>Build</h2>

<p>The Lean Startup has the concept of a Minimal Viable Product or MVP.
The idea is that you never build more than what is needed to learn.
While we would all love to produce a beautiful finished and polished
piece of work, it comes at a price. The price is time and waste.</p>

<p>What benefit is it to create a &lsquo;wonderful&rsquo; product that no one will ever buy?
The end result is a tremendous investment in time with the end result of
learning that no one wants it. One could have learned this in a fraction
of the time and expense with an MVP.</p>

<h2>Measure</h2>

<p>Learn to measure and track meaningful things that will guide you in determining
if your product is proving successful. The book covers in detail the difference
between actionable metrics and vanity metrics. In order for a metric to be
actionable it must demonstrate clear cause and effect. Otherwise the metric
could lead you astray giving you a false sense of security.</p>

<h2>Learn</h2>

<p>Are you taking what you&rsquo;ve learned from your metrics to build an even better
product or are you randomly dropping in product features and strategies simply
because it &lsquo;feels right&rsquo; or it sounds like a &lsquo;good idea&rsquo;? At what point do
you make a fundamental change to your business based on the learning done
so far? What have we learned and what are we doing about it?</p>

<p>I hope you enjoyed this little article.</p>

<p>The last couple of weeks I&rsquo;ve been sticking to a pattern that has worked well
for me for releasing new blog content. On Mondays I&rsquo;ll post an article on self
improvement or health related topic. Wednesday I&rsquo;ll release an article for
folks doing software development and Fridays I&rsquo;ll close out the week with
something fun such as some interesting Youtube videos. Thanks to all my
return visitors. I hope you come back soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Pareto Principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T17:51:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a very powerful principle and it can be quite
transformative if you can learn to spot it and apply it to your daily life.
I first became aware of the Pareto Principle when I worked as a
developer at a company in the business of selling software to mid-level
manufacturing companies.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/pareto-principle.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>The Pareto Principle goes by many names such the 80/20 principle, Pareto&rsquo;s
Law, the law of the vital few and more. What it basically states is that
20% of the causes drive 80% of the effects. Another way of saying this is
that 20% of the inputs results in 80% of the outputs. For example a company
will likely find that 20% of their customers generate 80% of their income.</p>

<p>Microsoft found that fixing the top 20% of the most reported bugs eliminated
80% of the related errors and crashes in a given <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">system</a>.
Other observations have included things such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>20% of motorists cause 80% of traffic accidents</li>
<li>20% of criminals account for 80% of the value of all crime</li>
<li>20% of the clothes a person person owns is worn 80% of the time.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was recently reintroduced to the principle upon reading Tim Ferriss&#8217; book,
The 4-hour Workweek. He drives home the idea of eliminating waste through its
use and this is one way the principle can be transformative.</p>

<p>If a company realizes that 80% of it&rsquo;s time is consumed by 20% of its customers
then it must ask itself the hard question, &ldquo;Should we part ways with those clients.&rdquo;
If those clients are contribiting only a small amount of the revenue but
are capitalizing most of the time then indeed parting ways maybe the smart choice.</p>

<p>We may find in our own daily lives that 20% of our activities consume
80% of our time. These activities could consist of web surfing, answering
emails, and other unproductive activities. Should we remove or greatly
limit these activities then we could recoop signifact chunks of time
as well as reduce our stress.</p>

<p>Give it some thought and see if this principle can be applied to an area
of your life, activity or business.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
