<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Income | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/tags/income/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-21T21:55:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Passion to Income: Convergence]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/14/from-passion-to-income/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-14T20:46:52-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/14/from-passion-to-income</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Choose a job you love, and you will never have to work a day in your life.</p><footer><strong>Confucius</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>One of my recent reads is the book <em>&lsquo;The $100 Startup&rsquo;</em>.
It&rsquo;s inspiring and full of great advice
on starting a business on shoe string budget. The author
has done a great deal of research finding people followed their dreams made
it as well as how they did it.</p>

<p>One of the ideas covered in the book is called <em>&lsquo;Convergence&rsquo;</em>. This
occurs when a person able to generate income from the thing or things he
is passionate about.</p>

<p>While there are many ways to make money, I would say most would either be boring or
life draining. Being stuck in a job or career that brings you no joy is
just grueling and painful. That&rsquo;s where the daily grind of 8 to 5 will just burn you
out after a few years.</p>

<p>On the other side is being passionate about things which bring you no income. While I may love
walks in the park, I doubt I&rsquo;ll ever make much money at it.</p>

<p>However, don&rsquo;t be too quick to quit on that crazy idea. It often
just takes a little creativity to pull it off.
<a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/richest-youtube-stars-2014-3#19-theradbrad-2">Bradley &ldquo;The Rad Brad&rdquo; Colburn</a>, for example,
makes between $137 thousand - $1.38 million dollars a year doing humorous video game &lsquo;walkthroughs&rsquo; on YouTube.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/convergence.jpg" width="592" height="420"></p>

<p>Here are the steps.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;1. List out the things you love to do and are passionate about.<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;2. Figure out which are likely to make you income.<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;3. Do that.</p>

<p>I did something similar in the summer of 1999. After working at several unsatisfying odd jobs
over the years, I realized I needed good income and fulfilling work. I had no formal education but
a lot of interest in various things. I was a good artist but I figured there was no decent income
in that and the demand didn&rsquo;t seem high for it at the time. I did like computers and had above
average knowledge so I thought, &ldquo;Maybe I&rsquo;ll try that&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I bought various computer science books, studied in the evenings and landed a job in
tech support about 6 months later. From there, I continued studying,
was promoted to the software development department. I attended
several classes at a couple of local 2 year colleges.</p>

<p>To this day I continue expanding my skill set, looking at what&rsquo;s in demand and doing that. I&rsquo;ve
greatly expanded my income and I love what I do. You can do it too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
