<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Funny | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/categories/funny/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-24T21:30:39-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Immortalize a Former Coworker]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/03/21/how-immortalize-a-former-coworker/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-21T15:12:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/03/21/how-immortalize-a-former-coworker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/shawshank_red.jpg" width="473" height="358"></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Sometimes it makes me sad, though, Andy being gone. I have to remind<br/>myself that some birds aren&rsquo;t meant to be caged, that&rsquo;s all. Their<br/>feathers are just too bright and when they fly away, the part<br/>of you that knows it was a sin to lock them up does rejoice&hellip;but still,<br/>the place you live is that much more drab and empty that they&rsquo;re gone.</p><footer><strong>Red</strong> <cite>The Shawshank Redemption</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>There are times when you miss a fomer coworker. Maybe they were really good at what
they did. Perhaps they were clever, upbeat or eccentric. Or maybe they offered much
needed comic relief.</p>

<p>A couple of months ago one of my coworkers decided to take a couple years off from work to
strike it on his own to build a product he&rsquo;s passionate about without the
daily pressures of a job.</p>

<p>He&rsquo;s a young guy with his own offbeat sense of humor. Those of us that worked with him
found him quite hilarious.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know what inspired me to do this but I drew a caricature of him on dry erase
painted wall of our office and I every so often I update the captions on it. People read
it have a good laugh and it&rsquo;s almost like he never left.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hpisms_1.jpg" width="900"></p>

<p>Now, this coworker is a young guy just a few years out of college. He is an atheist who
seems to disappear into his room for days according to his roommate. He loves to play
video games downing a six pack of Monster Energy drinks and a family size bag of Skittles&hellip;
ok, I made up that last bit.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hpisms_2.jpg" width="900"></p>

<p>I theorize that he must be keeping a joural of all the wrongs inflicted on him by the
world yet I have absolutely no proof whatsoever. He apparently is not compelled to give
Christmas presents to his family yet for some strange reason has no problem accepting
them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
