<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Funny | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/categories/funny/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-03T09:49:56-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Blow Against Grammar Nazis]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/03/22/a-blow-against-grammar-nazis/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T15:06:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/03/22/a-blow-against-grammar-nazis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/raine.jpg" width="473" title="" ></p>

<p><blockquote><p>You probably heard we ain&rsquo;t in the prisoner-takin&#8217; business;<br/>we in the killin&#8217; Nazi business. And cousin, business is a-boomin&#8217;.</p><footer><strong>Lt. Aldo Raine</strong> <cite>Inglourious Basterds</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I recognize that grammar is important. Use of proper grammar not only
sounds pleasant, it also ensures a higher degree of
clarity on the subject one is addressing. So while I am not saying grammar doesn&rsquo;t
matter, I would like to address several myths and misconceptions regarding grammar
as well as some thoughts regarding the correction of another&rsquo;s grammar in everyday
speech.</p>

<p>Alright, see if this sounds familiar. You&rsquo;re having a discussion with someone and the
grammar Nazi all of a sudden objects to something you&rsquo;ve said.
As if you&rsquo;ve offended his mother he says, &ldquo;No, that&rsquo;s not
correct. There is no such word as that,&rdquo; or he&rsquo;ll say, &ldquo;You&rsquo;re using that incorrectly,&rdquo;
or some such claim.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to give you a couple of good ways to defend yourself so you don&rsquo;t
feel completely victimized. After all this is &lsquo;merica!
And there&rsquo;s nothing Americans like more than kill&#8217;n some Nazis.</p>

<h2>That Word Does Not Exist</h2>

<p>First off, what the Nazi really means is that the word doesn&rsquo;t exist in the
dictionary. Now that assumes that presence in a dictionary is the absolute
authority on whether a word exists or not, which it isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>Most English dictionaries include only those words that meet certain criteria
of <a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/help/faq/words_in.htm">usage</a>. Because of this
words that are still in the process of becoming established are often omitted.
Some words are so informal or specialized that they are rarely documented in
professionally edited works. However these words are as real as those that have
gained entry with the only difference that they haven&rsquo;t met the strict criteria for
being <a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/help/faq/real_words.htm">entered</a>.</p>

<h2>Nonstandard Words</h2>

<p>A nonstandard word is defined as:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Not conforming to the speech or grammar of educated people and often<br/>regarded as a marker of low social status.</p><footer><strong>Random House Webster&rsquo;s College Dictionary</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll notice the connotation of social status in connection to nonstandard words.
I&rsquo;ll comment on that a bit later.</p>

<p>Here are some examples of nonstandard words:</p>

<ul>
<li>ain&rsquo;t - You ain&rsquo;t the law.</li>
<li>nohow - We could nohow make out his handwriting.</li>
<li>irregardless - I&rsquo;ll buy it irregardless of cost.</li>
</ul>


<p>However allowances are given to the use of nonstandard words in certain situations.
In fiction, use of nonstandard words is allowed in the dialogue of characters so as
to reflect the character&rsquo;s background and level of education.
Educated speakers will often use nonstandard forms to set a popular or informal
<a href="http://www.thefreedictionary.com/nonstandard">tone</a>.</p>

<p>Nonstandard forms can be perfectly acceptable in certain regions. An example is the
unrecognized contraction of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Y%27all">&ldquo;y&#8217;all&rdquo;</a>. It is the
nonstandard form of the contraction &lsquo;you&rsquo; and &lsquo;all&rsquo;, yet commonly
used throughout the southern United States.</p>

<p>It is the view of some linguists that what is considered standard english is a
matter of societal opinion.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It is important to understand that identifying a dialect as standard or<br/>nonstandard is a sociological judgment, not a linguistic one.</p><footer><strong>F. Parker and K. Riley</strong> <cite>Linguistics for Non-Linguists</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Take for example the rule against the use of double negatives. It says that two
negatives cancel each other out. &ldquo;I can&rsquo;t get no satisfaction.&rdquo;, basically means that
I can get satisfaction. However this rule didn&rsquo;t see application until after the 17th
century when certain writers sought to relate the rules of the language to logic and
<a href="http://blog.oxforddictionaries.com/2012/02/grammar-myths-3/">mathematics</a>.
Prior to that it was common to use double negatives as emphasizing a negative.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Ther nas no man nowher so vertuous…</p><footer><strong>Chaucer</strong> <cite>The Friar’s Tale</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>I never was nor never will be.</p><footer><strong>Shakespeare</strong> <cite>Richard III</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll notice the use of double negatives in some of these great literary works of
the English language.</p>

<p>My point is that nonstandard words do have a place in everyday speech and it doesn&rsquo;t
automatically make them completely unacceptable.</p>

<h2>Rules for the Sake of Rules</h2>

<p>As I said earlier the reason for grammar is that it provides the rules of language
structure so that individuals can understand one another. The more a person diverges
from proper grammar the greater his risk of either being misunderstood or not understood
at all.</p>

<p>However, the Nazi will commonly object to perfectly understandable speech merely
on the fact that it is not, in the strictest sense, perfect grammar. I believe
this to be an unreasonable expectation of informal speech.</p>

<p>I liken this to driving with the passenger objecting every time you drive a mile or two
over the speed limit, questioning your ability to drive and commenting on how you
are hazard to other drivers on the road. All because you are not strictly following
the rules of the road.</p>

<h2>Train of Thought</h2>

<p>Questioning someone&rsquo;s grammar usage is disruptive to the current
conversation. Realize that whatever you were discussing has now taken a backseat
to a grammar lesson. Continue this action long enough and you&rsquo;re liable to not
get much done or waste others&#8217; time.</p>

<p>I would especially question this practice in a work setting such as a meeting.
Is the subject you&rsquo;re meeting about so unimportant that it&rsquo;s acceptable to sidetrack
it with a discussion on grammar? However, if you&rsquo;re the boss then feel free to
teach as you&rsquo;re paying your employees to attend this lesson.</p>

<h2>Etiquette</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>Unless he is teaching an English class,<br/>a gentleman does not corrects another person&rsquo;s grammar.</p><footer><strong>John Bridges &amp; Bryan Curtis</strong> <cite>As a Gentleman Would Say: Responses to Life&rsquo;s Important (and Sometimes Awkward) Situations</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Manners is the grease which eases the friction of human relations. Many times those who
use poor grammar are individuals to whom English is a second language. Other times they
may have only a rudimentary education. Drawing attention to their use
of poor grammar is tantamount to calling them stupid or of lower class than you.
This is compounded when such corrections are done in the presence of others.</p>

<p>If someone calls your grammar into question then feel free to call their etiquette
into question. Be an Etiquette Nazi and see how they like it.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t behave like the guy at the gym who walks up to someone criticizing their form or
workout without being solicited to do so.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s no such thing as a word that does not exist, only words that are not
commonly used. There are cases where nonstandard forms are perfectly acceptable. Grammar
helps us understand each other, it is not just a bunch of rules for the sake of rules.
Interrupting someone&rsquo;s train of thought is disruptive and can be considered rude.</p>

<p>In closing I leave you with this funny skit by the guys at College Humor. Notice the Nazi
falls victim to his own unrelenting criticisms because even the most pedantic grammar critic
will at some point make his own grammatical transgression.</p>

<p>Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>

<p>
<div class="ratio-4-3 embed-video-container" onclick="var myAnchor = document.getElementById('N4vf8N6GpdM');var tmpDiv = document.createElement('div');tmpDiv.innerHTML = '&lt;iframe style=&quot;vertical-align:top;width:100%;height:100%;position:absolute;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/N4vf8N6GpdM?autoplay=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;';myAnchor.parentNode.replaceChild(tmpDiv.firstChild, myAnchor);return false;" title="click here to play">
<a class="youtube-lazy-link" style="width:100%;height:100%;background:#000 url(http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/N4vf8N6GpdM/0.jpg) center center no-repeat;background-size:contain;position:absolute" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N4vf8N6GpdM" id="N4vf8N6GpdM" onclick="return false;">
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-div"></div>
<div class="youtube-lazy-link-info">Grammar Nazis</div>
</a>
<div class="video-info" >CLICK FOR THAT CHEESY MEATY GOODNESS http://bit.ly/ykCeQ2
See more http://www.collegehumor.com   
 
LIKE us on: http://www.facebook.com/collegehumor
FOLLOW us on: http://www.twitter.com/collegehumor
FOLLOW us on: http://www.tumblr.com/collegehumor</div>
</div>

</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Immortalize a Former Coworker]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/03/21/how-immortalize-a-former-coworker/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-21T15:12:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/03/21/how-immortalize-a-former-coworker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/shawshank_red.jpg" width="473" height="358"></p>

<p><blockquote><p>Sometimes it makes me sad, though, Andy being gone. I have to remind<br/>myself that some birds aren&rsquo;t meant to be caged, that&rsquo;s all. Their<br/>feathers are just too bright and when they fly away, the part<br/>of you that knows it was a sin to lock them up does rejoice&hellip;but still,<br/>the place you live is that much more drab and empty that they&rsquo;re gone.</p><footer><strong>Red</strong> <cite>The Shawshank Redemption</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>There are times when you miss a fomer coworker. Maybe they were really good at what
they did. Perhaps they were clever, upbeat or eccentric. Or maybe they offered much
needed comic relief.</p>

<p>A couple of months ago one of my coworkers decided to take a couple years off from work to
strike it on his own to build a product he&rsquo;s passionate about without the
daily pressures of a job.</p>

<p>He&rsquo;s a young guy with his own offbeat sense of humor. Those of us that worked with him
found him quite hilarious.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know what inspired me to do this but I drew a caricature of him on dry erase
painted wall of our office and I every so often I update the captions on it. People read
it have a good laugh and it&rsquo;s almost like he never left.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hpisms_1.jpg" width="900"></p>

<p>Now, this coworker is a young guy just a few years out of college. He is an atheist who
seems to disappear into his room for days according to his roommate. He loves to play
video games downing a six pack of Monster Energy drinks and a family size bag of Skittles&hellip;
ok, I made up that last bit.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hpisms_2.jpg" width="900"></p>

<p>I theorize that he must be keeping a joural of all the wrongs inflicted on him by the
world yet I have absolutely no proof whatsoever. He apparently is not compelled to give
Christmas presents to his family yet for some strange reason has no problem accepting
them.</p>

<p>Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
