<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Bake Free | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/tags/bake-free/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-30T23:21:46-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Low Carb Oatmeal Recipes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/03/5-low-carb-oatmeal-recipes/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-03T14:30:56-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/03/5-low-carb-oatmeal-recipes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before going low carb, I used to enjoy the occasional bowl of oatmeal.
Depending on the type of low carb diet you practice and how strict
the amount of carbs are, it may not be a choice. A typical serving
comes in at 20 plus or so net carbs. This prompted me to take a look
around the inter webs and look some low carb alternatives.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Grain-Free-Instant-Cinnamon-Oatmeal.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>This first recipe uses chai seeds, flax meal, shredded unsweetened
coconut and cinnamon. Add some hot water, a bit of unsweetened
coconut milk, sweetener  and you might have a <a href="http://holisticallyengineered.com/2013/05/instant-cinnamon-oatmeal-low-carb.html">winner</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/low-carb-overnight-flax-meal-1-704x1024.jpg" width="400"></p>

<p>This next recipe is called ‘Overnight Flaxmeal’.
It incorporates yogurt, flaxseed meal, unsweetened almond milk,
protein powder, sweetener and raspberries.
It’s a simple recipe and the
<a href="http://the-lowcarb-diet.com/low-carb-overnight-flax-meal">instructions</a>
are pretty straight forward.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/coconut_oatmeal.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>Another showing some promise is ‘Coconut Breakfast Porridge’.
<a href="http://freshfitnhealthy.com/2014/04/coconut-breakfast-porridge-low-carb-oatmeal">This recipe</a> uses unsweetened shredded coconut,  unsweetened
vanilla almond milk, Coconut Flour.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/noatmeal-finished.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>This <a href="http://delishix.com/noatmeal-no-oatmeal-recipe">one</a> is a
bit trickier since you have to grind up various nuts
in a food processor and you’ll have to incorporate eggs into as well.
The ingredients in this recipe are walnuts, pecans, almonds, pepitas,
flax meal, cinnamon, almond butter, eggs, sweetener.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/low_carb_coconut_oatmeal.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>This final one is very simple straightforward
<a href="http://www.foodiefiasco.com/low-carb-coconut-oatmeal">recipe</a>
with minimal ingredient. The items needed are coconut,
coconut milk, water and coconut flour.</p>

<p>Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chocolate Ganache Recipe]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/02/chocolate-ganache-recipe/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T15:13:50-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/02/chocolate-ganache-recipe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ganache is a chocolate mixture used in several deserts. Warm ganache can be lightly poured on cake to create a glaze or it can be used as filling in cakes such as a molten lava cake. It can also drizzled on ice cream as tasty topping. Cold ganache can be rolled into chocolate truffles.</p>

<p>My current favorite low carb sweetener I use in cooking is Sin-Free Sugar. It has a flavor very close to sugar, is all natural and calorie free. I prefer it to Truvia for various reasons. Truvia consists of erythritol, stevia and natural flavors. I notice when using Truvia in recipes that require a lot sweetener that it tends to become gritty upon cooling. I don’t run into this issue with Sin-Free since it consists of a blend of natural sugars your body does not absorb. For more information you can check out the Sin-Free Sugar website: <a href="https://www.sinfreesugar.com/">https://www.sinfreesugar.com/</a> .</p>

<p>The mixture will thicken to harden in the fridge. You can gently melt some in the microwave when you want to use it on your low carb deserts or you an add some to your coffee with a bit of cream for a real tasty coffee mocha.</p>

<p>The recipes yields about 29 oz with under 1 net carb for 2 oz serving.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/ganache_smaller.jpg" width="300"></p>

<h4>Ingredients</h4>

<ul>
<li>8 oz unsweetened chocolate</li>
<li>1 cup heavy cream</li>
<li>1 teaspoon vanilla</li>
<li>2 cups of Sin-Free Sugar</li>
<li>2 tablespoons SweetLeaf</li>
<li>4 tablespoons salted butter</li>
</ul>


<h4>Steps:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Chop unsweetened chocolate and butter, place into a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>Mix dry ingredients together (Sin-Free Sugar, SweetLeaf) and place into a medium saucepan.</li>
<li>Add wet ingredients (heavy cream, vanilla) to saucepan, Stir until dry and wet ingredients are mixed well so that no large lumps are present.</li>
<li>Heat the mixture while stirring. When mixture bubbles and begins to climb the sides of the saucepan, turn off stove and remove from heat.</li>
<li>Add hot mixture to mixing bowl containing chocolate pieces and wait 1 minute.</li>
<li>Stir mixture in bowl until all chocolate is melted and well incorporated.</li>
<li>Whisk until smooth and slightly thickened.</li>
<li>Leave until a bit cooled and then move to a container and store in refrigerator.</li>
</ol>


<p>Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
