<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Biohacking | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/categories/biohacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-10T16:14:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Paleo Diet and the Missing Link]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/15/the-paleo-diet-and-the-missing-link/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-15T15:40:36-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/15/the-paleo-diet-and-the-missing-link</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Once you have to start counting calories,<br/>it takes away from the joy of eating.</p><footer><strong>Mireille Guiliano</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The Paleo Diet is an effort to eat as our prehistoric ancestors did prior to the
advent of farming. Food such as meats, fish, nuts, leafy greens, veggies, and seeds
are foods typically found on the diet.</p>

<p>One of the things I believe is missing from the diet is the eating pattern our
ancestors practiced. You see there were typically periods of feast and famine.
After a successful hunt the group would feast. Then one might expect a certain amount
of time would pass before another successful hunt would take place and thus a
time of fasting would occur.</p>

<p>The dietary practice of intermittent fasting attempts to implement in some form this type of
eating pattern. Generally the diet limits eating to an 8 hour window with a 16 hour
fast in between.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/leangains.jpg" width="473" height="358"></p>

<p style="text-align:center;">
   Martin Berkhan
</p>


<h2>Dietary Myths</h2>

<p>Martin Berkhan, a nutritional consultant, magazine writer and personal trainer. Is
a strong proponent of this diet and has achieved remarkable results practicing it.
On Martin Berkhan&rsquo;s web site <a href="http://www.leangains.com/">Lean Gains</a>, he goes about
shattering various diet myths.</p>

<p>Some of my favorites are:</p>

<h3>Myth: Eating frequent small meals helps you loose weight</h3>

<p>An extenisve review of various meal frequencies and its effect on metabolism
showed no effect between eating several small meals or a couple of large ones.</p>

<p>To quote the review, <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9155494">&ldquo;More importantly, studies using
whole-body calorimetry and doubly-labelled water to assess total 24 h
energy expenditure find <strong>no difference between nibbling and gorging.</strong>&rdquo;</a></p>

<h3>Myth: Eat smaller meals more often for hunger control.</h3>

<p>Current research suggests the opposite. Eating more often leads to increased
hunger.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20339363">&ldquo;Collectively, these data suggest that higher protein
intake promotes satiety and challenge the concept that
increasing the number of eating occasions enhances satiety
in overweight and obese men&rdquo;</a></p>

<h2>Examples</h2>

<p>The following are some examples of the form this pattern of feeding and exercise would
look like:</p>

<h4>Pattern 1</h4>

<ul>
<li>Fasting - Fast from 8 p.m. the night before till 10 -11 a.m. or so and take 10g BCAAs.</li>
<li>Train - Hot the gym and get your workout in.</li>
<li>Meal One – 1 p.m.</li>
<li>Meal Two – 4 p.m.</li>
<li>Meal Three – 7 p.m.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Pattern 2</h4>

<ul>
<li>Pre-Workout Meal - 12 Noon.</li>
<li>Train</li>
<li>Meal Two – 4 p.m.</li>
<li>Meal Three – 7/8 p.m.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Pattern 3</h4>

<ul>
<li>Meal One – Noon.</li>
<li>Meal Two – 3 p.m.</li>
<li>Train</li>
<li>Meal Three – 7/8 p.m.</li>
</ul>


<p>Martin Berkhan claims many benefits to this type of dieting such as weight loss,
better hormonal response and improved blood sugar levels. He cites various
scientific studies and testimonials from his clients.</p>

<p>For more information visit <a href="http://www.leangains.com/">www.leangains.com</a>.</p>

<p>Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[O2 Trainer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/02/o2-trainer/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T15:03:45-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/02/o2-trainer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently received the O2 Trainer as a present this past Christmas.
The idea of this product is to strengthen your diaphragm and lung muscles via resistance as you pull air into your lungs.
It consists of a mouth piece and interchangeable modules which provide 14 stages of resistance.
If you visit www.o2trainer.com you find various studies using the product, testimonials and instructions.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/insp_muscle_trainer_smaller.jpeg" width="600"></p>

<p style="text-align:center;">
   O2 Trainer
</p>


<p>My purpose for the product is improving athletic performance.
I&rsquo;m currently a blue belt in Kenpo Karate, a style which utilizes quick hand strikes and kicks.
Sparring can be quite intense and can quickly cause one to run out of breath.
Tonight I started the first breathing exercise. Starting with module number 11, I did 4 sets of 12 reps.
One breathes in hard and then exhales. Once I was done and for a few hours after, I could feel that my diagram and abs got a good workout.
I look forward to continued use of this product and effect it has on my performance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
