<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Books | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-10T18:27:25-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Pareto Principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T17:51:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a very powerful principle and it can be quite
transformative if you can learn to spot it and apply it to your daily life.
I first became aware of the Pareto Principle when I worked as a
developer at a company in the business of selling software to mid-level
manufacturing companies.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/pareto-principle.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>The Pareto Principle goes by many names such the 80/20 principle, Pareto&rsquo;s
Law, the law of the vital few and more. What it basically states is that
20% of the causes drive 80% of the effects. Another way of saying this is
that 20% of the inputs results in 80% of the outputs. For example a company
will likely find that 20% of their customers generate 80% of their income.</p>

<p>Microsoft found that fixing the top 20% of the most reported bugs eliminated
80% of the related errors and crashes in a given <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">system</a>.
Other observations have included things such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>20% of motorists cause 80% of traffic accidents</li>
<li>20% of criminals account for 80% of the value of all crime</li>
<li>20% of the clothes a person person owns is worn 80% of the time.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was recently reintroduced to the principle upon reading Tim Ferriss&#8217; book,
The 4-hour Workweek. He drives home the idea of eliminating waste through its
use and this is one way the principle can be transformative.</p>

<p>If a company realizes that 80% of it&rsquo;s time is consumed by 20% of its customers
then it must ask itself the hard question, &ldquo;Should we part ways with those clients.&rdquo;
If those clients are contribiting only a small amount of the revenue but
are capitalizing most of the time then indeed parting ways maybe the smart choice.</p>

<p>We may find in our own daily lives that 20% of our activities consume
80% of our time. These activities could consist of web surfing, answering
emails, and other unproductive activities. Should we remove or greatly
limit these activities then we could recoop signifact chunks of time
as well as reduce our stress.</p>

<p>Give it some thought and see if this principle can be applied to an area
of your life, activity or business.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Stay Poor]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/17/how-to-stay-poor/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T19:33:19-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/17/how-to-stay-poor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following are some ideas regarding social economic classes and spending patterns
introduced in various books such as <em>Rich Dad Poor Dad</em>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/poor_a.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>Here we see the typical young person or the poor. The income on the left
being consumed almost completely by basic recurring expenses.
The net or left over income is very little.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/middle_class_a.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>As the individual begins to earn more income his economic status improves and
his net income grows since he is now outpacing his recurring expenses. Life is
good, he can afford things he could not before. He can now qualify for credit
and loans given this higher income bracket. However, he then falls into the trap
middle class america falls into&hellip;debt.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/middle_class_b.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>He begins to engage in financial commitments that generate a
recurring bill such as buying a home, leasing a car, loans, credit card
purchases, etc.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/middle_class_c.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>These long term commitments now generate a recurring bill which consumes his
monthly net income, lowering its margin and causing him to be broke&hellip;again.</p>

<p>I hate to use the term &ldquo;rich&rdquo; because it&rsquo;s a little banal and sometimes not
accurate of this class of individual. Let&rsquo;s just call him the &lsquo;well off&rsquo;. This is one prudent strategy
to build solvency and build economic independence.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/middle_class_to_rich_b.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>Here the person, instead of investing in future financial commitments, tackles
existing commitment to pay them down or off and then invests in income generating
assets. Preferably assets that passively generate income. In other words assets that
will generate income and not consume much of his time. Things like royality rights,
stocks, bonds, intellectual property, real estate and such.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/middle_class_to_rich_c.jpg" width="600"></p>

<p>By doing this he now lowers his recurring debt increasing his net income. Also he
begins earning money passively thus boosting his current income.</p>

<p>I hope this might be useful to some you. Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
