<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Making Money | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/categories/making-money/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-20T00:17:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build Measure Learn]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/12/build-measure-learn/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-12T14:34:48-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/12/build-measure-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/build-measure-learn.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>Some months ago I came across a list of top books recommended by
successful entrepreneurs. Towards the top of this list was the
book &lsquo;The Lean Startup&rsquo;. I highly recommend this book to anyone
looking to start their own business or anyone involved in management.</p>

<p>One of the major concepts in the lean startup method is what&rsquo;s referred to
as the Build-Measure-Learn feedback loop. The basic idea is a cycle of
of building a product, measuring success then learning from this measurement
and other actions so as to build a better product and finally start
the cycle again. It is a way managing uncertainty and risk.</p>

<p>Realize that it&rsquo;s the speed at which this cycle occurs that most likely
determines success. A startup or new venture has a limited amount of time
and/or funds in order to become a viable concern. Once these resources are
consumed and no other options are present; the startup is done. This is why
speed is of essence.</p>

<p>While the cycle seems straight forward, each of these points on the cycle
has it&rsquo;s challenges.</p>

<h2>Build</h2>

<p>The Lean Startup has the concept of a Minimal Viable Product or MVP.
The idea is that you never build more than what is needed to learn.
While we would all love to produce a beautiful finished and polished
piece of work, it comes at a price. The price is time and waste.</p>

<p>What benefit is it to create a &lsquo;wonderful&rsquo; product that no one will ever buy?
The end result is a tremendous investment in time with the end result of
learning that no one wants it. One could have learned this in a fraction
of the time and expense with an MVP.</p>

<h2>Measure</h2>

<p>Learn to measure and track meaningful things that will guide you in determining
if your product is proving successful. The book covers in detail the difference
between actionable metrics and vanity metrics. In order for a metric to be
actionable it must demonstrate clear cause and effect. Otherwise the metric
could lead you astray giving you a false sense of security.</p>

<h2>Learn</h2>

<p>Are you taking what you&rsquo;ve learned from your metrics to build an even better
product or are you randomly dropping in product features and strategies simply
because it &lsquo;feels right&rsquo; or it sounds like a &lsquo;good idea&rsquo;? At what point do
you make a fundamental change to your business based on the learning done
so far? What have we learned and what are we doing about it?</p>

<p>I hope you enjoyed this little article.</p>

<p>The last couple of weeks I&rsquo;ve been sticking to a pattern that has worked well
for me for releasing new blog content. On Mondays I&rsquo;ll post an article on self
improvement or health related topic. Wednesday I&rsquo;ll release an article for
folks doing software development and Fridays I&rsquo;ll close out the week with
something fun such as some interesting Youtube videos. Thanks to all my
return visitors. I hope you come back soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Pareto Principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T17:51:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a very powerful principle and it can be quite
transformative if you can learn to spot it and apply it to your daily life.
I first became aware of the Pareto Principle when I worked as a
developer at a company in the business of selling software to mid-level
manufacturing companies.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/pareto-principle.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>The Pareto Principle goes by many names such the 80/20 principle, Pareto&rsquo;s
Law, the law of the vital few and more. What it basically states is that
20% of the causes drive 80% of the effects. Another way of saying this is
that 20% of the inputs results in 80% of the outputs. For example a company
will likely find that 20% of their customers generate 80% of their income.</p>

<p>Microsoft found that fixing the top 20% of the most reported bugs eliminated
80% of the related errors and crashes in a given <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">system</a>.
Other observations have included things such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>20% of motorists cause 80% of traffic accidents</li>
<li>20% of criminals account for 80% of the value of all crime</li>
<li>20% of the clothes a person person owns is worn 80% of the time.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was recently reintroduced to the principle upon reading Tim Ferriss&#8217; book,
The 4-hour Workweek. He drives home the idea of eliminating waste through its
use and this is one way the principle can be transformative.</p>

<p>If a company realizes that 80% of it&rsquo;s time is consumed by 20% of its customers
then it must ask itself the hard question, &ldquo;Should we part ways with those clients.&rdquo;
If those clients are contribiting only a small amount of the revenue but
are capitalizing most of the time then indeed parting ways maybe the smart choice.</p>

<p>We may find in our own daily lives that 20% of our activities consume
80% of our time. These activities could consist of web surfing, answering
emails, and other unproductive activities. Should we remove or greatly
limit these activities then we could recoop signifact chunks of time
as well as reduce our stress.</p>

<p>Give it some thought and see if this principle can be applied to an area
of your life, activity or business.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Passion to Income: Convergence]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/14/from-passion-to-income/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-14T20:46:52-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/02/14/from-passion-to-income</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Choose a job you love, and you will never have to work a day in your life.</p><footer><strong>Confucius</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>One of my recent reads is the book <em>&lsquo;The $100 Startup&rsquo;</em>.
It&rsquo;s inspiring and full of great advice
on starting a business on shoe string budget. The author
has done a great deal of research finding people followed their dreams made
it as well as how they did it.</p>

<p>One of the ideas covered in the book is called <em>&lsquo;Convergence&rsquo;</em>. This
occurs when a person able to generate income from the thing or things he
is passionate about.</p>

<p>While there are many ways to make money, I would say most would either be boring or
life draining. Being stuck in a job or career that brings you no joy is
just grueling and painful. That&rsquo;s where the daily grind of 8 to 5 will just burn you
out after a few years.</p>

<p>On the other side is being passionate about things which bring you no income. While I may love
walks in the park, I doubt I&rsquo;ll ever make much money at it.</p>

<p>However, don&rsquo;t be too quick to quit on that crazy idea. It often
just takes a little creativity to pull it off.
<a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/richest-youtube-stars-2014-3#19-theradbrad-2">Bradley &ldquo;The Rad Brad&rdquo; Colburn</a>, for example,
makes between $137 thousand - $1.38 million dollars a year doing humorous video game &lsquo;walkthroughs&rsquo; on YouTube.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/convergence.jpg" width="592" height="420"></p>

<p>Here are the steps.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;1. List out the things you love to do and are passionate about.<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;2. Figure out which are likely to make you income.<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;3. Do that.</p>

<p>I did something similar in the summer of 1999. After working at several unsatisfying odd jobs
over the years, I realized I needed good income and fulfilling work. I had no formal education but
a lot of interest in various things. I was a good artist but I figured there was no decent income
in that and the demand didn&rsquo;t seem high for it at the time. I did like computers and had above
average knowledge so I thought, &ldquo;Maybe I&rsquo;ll try that&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I bought various computer science books, studied in the evenings and landed a job in
tech support about 6 months later. From there, I continued studying,
was promoted to the software development department. I attended
several classes at a couple of local 2 year colleges.</p>

<p>To this day I continue expanding my skill set, looking at what&rsquo;s in demand and doing that. I&rsquo;ve
greatly expanded my income and I love what I do. You can do it too.</p>

<p>Feel free to drop some comments or questions below. And if you liked it then
please share on twitter, facebook or your prefered social media channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
