<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[80/20 | Very Good Indicators]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/tags/80-slash-20/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-21T19:42:26-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mentaware Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Pareto Principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T17:51:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.verygoodindicators.com/blog/2015/04/05/the-pareto-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a very powerful principle and it can be quite
transformative if you can learn to spot it and apply it to your daily life.
I first became aware of the Pareto Principle when I worked as a
developer at a company in the business of selling software to mid-level
manufacturing companies.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/pareto-principle.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>The Pareto Principle goes by many names such the 80/20 principle, Pareto&rsquo;s
Law, the law of the vital few and more. What it basically states is that
20% of the causes drive 80% of the effects. Another way of saying this is
that 20% of the inputs results in 80% of the outputs. For example a company
will likely find that 20% of their customers generate 80% of their income.</p>

<p>Microsoft found that fixing the top 20% of the most reported bugs eliminated
80% of the related errors and crashes in a given <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">system</a>.
Other observations have included things such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>20% of motorists cause 80% of traffic accidents</li>
<li>20% of criminals account for 80% of the value of all crime</li>
<li>20% of the clothes a person person owns is worn 80% of the time.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was recently reintroduced to the principle upon reading Tim Ferriss&#8217; book,
The 4-hour Workweek. He drives home the idea of eliminating waste through its
use and this is one way the principle can be transformative.</p>

<p>If a company realizes that 80% of it&rsquo;s time is consumed by 20% of its customers
then it must ask itself the hard question, &ldquo;Should we part ways with those clients.&rdquo;
If those clients are contribiting only a small amount of the revenue but
are capitalizing most of the time then indeed parting ways maybe the smart choice.</p>

<p>We may find in our own daily lives that 20% of our activities consume
80% of our time. These activities could consist of web surfing, answering
emails, and other unproductive activities. Should we remove or greatly
limit these activities then we could recoop signifact chunks of time
as well as reduce our stress.</p>

<p>Give it some thought and see if this principle can be applied to an area
of your life, activity or business.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
